随着科技的发展
As we advance our technology ever forward
你们是不是以为重新制造一个五十年前的发动机很容易?
you would think that remaking a 50-year old design should be easy?
但事情可远没有那么简单
But things are not quite as simple as they first seem.
当太空发射系统(SLS)还在研发中时
When the Space Launch System or the SLS was in development,
NASA招标寻求新的助推系统
NASA ran the advanced booster competition to find a new booster system,
当时三个竞标中有两款是液体发动机
and two of the three entries used liquid fuel engines.
液体的助推更安全 在出事的时候可以自行关闭
Liquid fuel boosters would be safer and could be shut down in the event of a problem,
而固推就做不到这点
unlike the solid rocket boosters which can't.
但与航天飞机的固推不同的是 新的助推只能使用一次
However unlike the space shuttle the new boosters would be single-use only,
并在返回地球时烧毁
and would burn up when they fell back to earth.
那么对于芯级 哪种液体发动机推力足够大呢?
But which liquid fuel engines would be powerful enough?
现役的大推力发动机还真不多
There really aren't any massive engines in use today.
可以使用四个定制的RS-25D发动机
The boosters could use four same modified RS-25D engines.
航天飞机的RS-25发动机
这些发动机是航天飞机项目中遗留下来的 还会用在SLS的芯级
Those left over from a space shuttle program which would also be used for the SLS's main core stage.
可尽管效率很高 这些发动机还是太复杂太贵了
But that will be very wasteful of a complex, expensive, and yet highly efficient engine.
韦恩赫尔·冯·布劳恩
与土星五号F-1发动机
我们已经有了能胜任这个任务的发动机了
Now we've already had an engine capable of doing the job,
隆重介绍洛克达因F-1发动机
the mighty Rocketdyne F-1,
在阿波罗项目中送人类去月球的巨大发动机
the huge engines which took men to the moon with the Apollo program.
它们从六十年代起才开始制造
But they haven't been built since the 1960s.
F-1发动机不但推力大 结构还很简单
The F-1 engines were not only extremely powerful but they were also simple,
所以就算一次性使用也不心疼 那我们为什么不重新造几个呢?
which meant they were cheap enough to be disposable, so why don't we just remake them?
曾有过谣言说《震惊！NASA把土星五号图纸丢了！》
Now there is a common myth which says NASA lost or threw away the blueprints,
这纯属胡扯
which of course is complete rubbish.
阿波罗项目从开始以来的所有设计文件还都留着
Every design document ever created for the Apollo program is still available.
可如果有图纸就能造 那他们肯定早就这么干了
But if it was just a case of wheeling out old designs they would have done that years ago.
但现在问题不是图纸 而是时间过了这么久 世界变化太大了
Now the problem is not the design, but it's for way in which the world has moved on,
因为工程师首次造出F-1发动机还是在六十年代
since the engineers first created those F-1 engines back in the 1960s.
当现代工程师知道老前辈们是如何造F-1发动机的时候
When a group of present-day rocket engineers looked at how they could recreate the iconic F-1 engines,
他们马上就能明白这五十多年的变化有多大了
they soon realized just how differently things were done some 50 years ago,
当时没有计算机辅助设计(CAD) 只有计算尺和各种试错试验
when there was no Computer-Aided Design, just slide rules and trial and error testing.
零件先设计 然后造出来 接着测试 在真正使用前经常改了无数次
Components were designed, built and then tested and then often modified before being used.
复杂的发动机部件组装 经常要把上百个小零件焊接起来
Complex engines sub assemblies were welded together from sometimes hundreds of smaller parts
该过程需要高技术的焊接工人 有时一个复杂焊点要花一整天
with skilled welders taking sometimes a day to complete one complex weld.
尽管NASA还有原始的设计图纸
Although they had the original blueprints,
但他们真正丢失的是当时工程师高效率制造发动机的"笔记"
what they found that was missing
was the notes made by the engineers as they effectively handcrafted every engine,
而每位工程师因个人习惯 癖好 各自的"笔记"都有所不同
each one slightly different with its own quirks and foibles.
当年制造F-1发动机的工匠们大都是非常高级的工程师 焊工 钳工
The original builders of the F-1 engines were highly skilled engineers, welders and fitters,
发动机是纯手工打造的 因为那时候只能这样
they did almost everything by hand because often that was the only way to do it back then.
而且为了赶工期 他们有很多自己的窍门
And in the rush to meet deadlines, they kept many of the tricks,
这些窍门能提高效率 这些经验只记在脑子里
that they used to get things to work and go together in their heads,
或者随手记在小纸条上 早就不知道扔哪了
or scribbled down on scraps of paper long since lost.
转眼五十年过去 那些工匠们不是早已退休 就是驾鹤西去了
Roll on 50 years, and all of those skilled people have long since retired and many have passed away,
随之带走的还有他们的技能与知识
taking their skills and knowledge with them.
搅拌摩擦焊
而在先进的现代制造技术帮助下 那些工人的技术很多都用不上了
With the advent of modern manufacturing techniques, many of those skills are no longer in use,
一种用于减少金属中的孔洞或者提高陶瓷材料密度的制造工艺
这提高了材料的机械性能和可加工性
热等静压
现在也很少有人还会
and few people today have them.
所以面对五十年前的蓝图我们发现
So faced with 50-year old blueprints we find
我们只是找不到那些能像当年那样造发动机的高级工人了
we just don't have the people with the skills that can make them in the same way anymore.
在对博物馆和遗留的F-1发动机进行仔细检查后
By detailed examination of the remaining F-1 engines from museums and storage,
现代工程师的确有能力制造新的F-1B发动机 如果它的确制造出来的话
our new engineers did discover enough to create a new F-1B engine should it ever be built.
计划中的F-1B发动机
在现代计算机建模与制造技术的帮助下
Using modern computer modeling and manufacturing techniques,
新发动机不但效率更高
the new engine could not only be more efficient.
816吨
推力还可以与升级后但从未使用的F-1A发动机的180万磅相媲美
It would be just as powerful as the uprated but unflown F-1A at 1.8 million pounds of thrust,
更重要的是 这个过程还可以把零件数量从5600个减少到仅仅40个
but more importantly it would reduce the number of manufactured parts from some 5,600 to just 40,
提高可靠性 减少制造成本
and increase its reliability and decrease costs in the process.
虽然最终NASA还是为SLS选择了固推
Although in the end NASA selected the solid rocket boosters for the SLS,
但这次实践告诉了我们 从已有的发动机基础上重新设计
this exercise proved that it's sometimes easier to redesign something from scratch
有时比重新制造一个旧的更简单一点
than it is to try and remake the past.
所以你对重制F-1发动机有何看法? 对本期短视频有何看法?
So what do you think of remaking the F-1 engines and also this new short video format,
欢迎在评论区留言
let me know in the comments.
感谢所有patreon的赞助者
And I just like to take time to thank all of our patreons for their ongoing support,
感谢大家的观看 希望大家关注 评分并分享
and thank all of you for watching and please subscribe, rate and share.